Guide to the Ellwood S. Harrar Papers, 1928 - 1975 UA.29.02.0024
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ellwood S. Harrar papers
1928 - 1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harrar, Ellwood S. (Ellwood Scott)
UA.29.02.0024
2 Linear Feet
Ellwood S. Harrar served as a Professor of Wood Technology at Duke University from 1936 to 1974, and as Dean of the Duke University School of Forestry from 1957 to 1967. He researched and published extensively on forestry and dendrology. The Ellwood S. Harrar Papers contain documents related to his interests in the lumber industry and wood production. As a Dean, he participated in the planning for the new Biological Sciences Building and frequently corresponded with contractors and vendors regarding its construction. The materials in the collection are primarily correspondence, but it also includes academic papers, biographical sketches, and photographs, among other materials. Major subjects include the U.S. wood industry, wood technology, and forest research. Major correspondents include the Navy Bureau of Ships, Swift and Company, J.P. Perry, J. George Harrar, and the Brunswick Pulp Research Fund. English.
2000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Ellwood S. Harrar Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1969 and 1974.
Biographical Note
Ellwood Scott "Scotty" Harrar was born on January 18, 1905 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He attended Oberlin College for two years, but received his bachelor's degree from the New York College of Forestry at Syracuse University. Syracuse also awarded Harrar his master's and doctoral degrees, in 1928 and 1936, respectively. Harrar taught at the College of Forestry at the University of Washington in Seattle from 1928 until 1936, when he joined the faculty of Duke University.
At Duke, Harrar began as an Associate Professor of Wood Technology, and in 1945 became a full Professor of Wood Technology. In 1957, he was named Dean of the Duke University Graduate School of Forestry. He served in this capacity until 1967, and in 1974 Harrar retired from teaching. In his 38-year career at Duke, Harrar left only once: during World War II, he served as Chief Administrative Engineer of the Airplane Division of the Curtiss Wright Corporation.
During his tenure at Duke, Harrar participated in a number of professional organizations, including the Society of American Foresters, of which he was elected Fellow in 1965. He also served as Secretary-Treasurer of the International Society of Wood Anatomists from 1938-1948, President of the North Carolina Forestry Council in 1958, and President of the Forest Products Research Society in 1959. Harrar published extensively, and his Textbook of Dendrology became a staple of forestry programs across the country. Other popular publications included his Guide to Southern Trees and his numerous articles on forestry and dendrology topics for the Encyclopedia Britannica.
Harrar was awarded an Honorary Doctorate of Science from his alma mater, Syracuse in 1961. In 1967, he was named a James B. Duke Professor, the highest honor awarded to faculty at Duke University. In 1974, Harrar donated his collection of over 5,000 wood samples to the Winterthur Museum in Winterthur, Delaware, for future researchers. Harrar died on February 5, 1975, at the age of seventy.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, papers, photographs, and other documents related to Ellwood S. Harrar's career as a professor of forestry and Dean of the School of Forestry at Duke University. It is organized into the following series: Series 1, Personal, 1928-1975; Series 2, Duke University, 1951-1974; and Series 3, Correspondence, 1946-1974.
Wood technology; Forest products industry -- United States; Forest products industry -- Research -- United States; Photographs; Forests and forestry -- Research -- United States; Harrar, Ellwood S. (Ellwood Scott); Harrar, Ellwood S. (Ellwood Scott); Duke University. School of Forestry; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Buildings -- History -- 20th century; Brunswick Pulp and Paper Company, Brunswick, Ga; United States. Navy Dept. Bureau of Ships; Swift & Company; Perry, Jesse P.; Harrar, J. George (Jacob George), 1906-
- Personal, 1928 - 1975
  Scope and Contents note
  This series features biographical information about Harrar. Included are biographical sketches, letters of congratulation, and Harrar's Ph.D. Thesis. The Personal series also includes administrative correspondence with Duke officials regarding sabbaticals, committee appointments, and retirement.
  Arrangement note
  The documents are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Biographical, 1967-1975 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1957-1975 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Administrative
      - Personal, 1957-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - James B. Duke Professorship Nomination, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Congratulatory
      - Appointment to Dean of Forestry, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Election to Presidency of Forest Products Research Society, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Honorary Doctorate of Science, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Personal, 1932-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Publications
      - Textbook of Dendrology, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Southern Trees, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Retirement, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Masters or Doctoral Thesis, 1928-1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Panels and Committees, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Publications, 1943-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Duke University, 1951-1974
  The Duke University series includes correspondence, photographs, and other papers that document Harrar's interactions with Duke University as a faculty member and Dean. Among the documents are extensive correspondence and several photographs related to the construction of and furnishings for the Biological Sciences Building. Also included are materials, mainly correspondence, about the School of Forestry, and its educational philosophy, curriculum, and funding. In 1965, the Duke School of Forestry hosted the International Symposium on Tropical Forestry, and this series includes papers, summaries of proceedings, and biographical sketches of the participants of this symposium.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Allen, George V., 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Biographies, Paper Summaries, Travel Plans, etc., 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Biology - Forestry Building, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bradley Plywood Corporation, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Broce, Thomas E., [University Development, 1961-1966] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Building [Biological Sciences Building] - Miscellaneous
    - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cherokee Flooring Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Darlington Veneer Company, Inc., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Duke University Staff and Faculty, Non-Forestry, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - E. L. Bruce Company, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Frank, William O., Architect, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Georgia-Pacific Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Georgia Plywood Corporation, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gross-Edens Controversy, 1963-1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Haig, I. T., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Hardwood Corporation of America, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Higgins Industries, Inc., 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Korstian, Clarence F., 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lilly Company, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Masonite Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miller Brothers, Inc., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Moseman, A. H., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Nickey Brothers, Inc. 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Papers, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Potlatch Forests, Inc., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Roddis-Plywood Corporation, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - School of Forestry
    - 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - 1966-1971 and undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Setter Brothers, Inc., 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Southern Plywoods, Inc., 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Standard Plywoods, Inc., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Statesville Plywood and Veneer Co., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Summaries of Proceedings, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Thomason Plywood Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Tropical Forestry Symposium - Miscellaneous, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - U.S. Plywood Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Virginia Plywood Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Vogt, William, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Von Canon, Fred, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Wallace, William, Engineer, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Wood-Mosaic Corporation, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Correspondence, 1946-1974
  The correspondence series contains letters to and from Harrar regarding his professional career as a researcher and forestry expert. Among Harrar's correspondents were those associated with the lumber industry, in regard to marketing, foreign resources, and technical problems related to wood. The series documents Harrar's work as a consultant to the Navy Bureau of Ships, Army Corps of Engineers, and the Army Engineer Research and Development Laboratories. The series also contains information about Harrar's participation with North Carolina's Governor's Advisory Committee on Forestry and the Presidential Commission on Increased Use of Agricultural Products.
  The documents are arranged alphabetically according to the name of either the individual or organization with which Harrar corresponded. The only exception is folder titled "[General] Correspondence - Miscellaneous," which is filed at the end of the series.
  - Active Investments, Inc., 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - American Institute of Biological Science, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Company, 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Bennett Place (Committee on Restoration), 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Brevard College, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Brunswick Pulp Research Fund, 1953-1966 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Bureau of Ships, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Charles Lathrop Pack Forestry Foundation, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Commonwealth Fund, 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Coman Lumber Company, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Congressional Correspondence, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Curtiss-Wright Aircraft Co. - Employment as Engineering Manager, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Dunn, Paul M., 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Fifth World Forestry Congress, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Forest History Foundation, Inc., 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - S. M. Frank and Company, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Governor's Advisory Committee on Forestry, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - International Association of Wood Anatomists, 1936-1947 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Harrar, J. George, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - The Lane Company, Inc., 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Lester Case, 1949-1958 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - [Folder removed] (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Mulford, Walter, 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Navy, Bureau of Ships
    - 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Perry, J. P., 1947-1971 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Presidential Commission, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - President's Commission, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Research Triangle Committee, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - General, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Scott Lumber Company, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Southeastern Forest Experiment Station, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Southern Railway System, Washington, D.C., 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Standard Fruit and Steamship Company, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - State of North Carolina, Department of Conservation and Development, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Swift and Company
    - 1949 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - 1951-68 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Technical Problems - Examples, 1953-1968 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - U.S. Army Biological Laboratories, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - U.S. Army Engineer Research and Development Laboratories, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Wellwood, Dr. R. W., 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Winterthur [The H. F. duPont Winterthur Museum, 1973 - 1974] (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - [General] Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 108)